Guide to the Houston Subdivision Plat Maps Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Houston Subdivision Plat Maps Collection
1900-1981
1900-1970
2007-027
James & Associates (Houston, Tex.); Houston Map Company
3.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection consists of six volumes of subdivision plat maps of developed areas of Houston, Texas recorded between approximately 1900 and 1970.
Historical Note:
James & Associates was a surveying and civil engineering firm that did business in Houston from approximately 1960 to 1985. The firm owned six bound volumes of subdivision plat maps, which documented many neighborhoods of the city, from the oldest downtown to the newer suburbs of the 1950s and 60s. The firm also did the civil engineering work for a residential subdivision in north Harris County known originally as “Thameswood, Section 1” and later as “Memorial Chase, Section 3.” Their work product included maps and engineering drawings for the subdivision. Lawrence B. James, the firm’s owner, donated the materials to the University of Houston Libraries in 2007.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Houston Map Company; James & Associates (Houston, Tex.)
Genre/Form of Material:
land surveys; plats (maps); technical drawings
Topical Term:
City planning; Land use -- Planning
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Lawrence B. James, December 2007
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of six volumes of subdivision plat maps of developed areas of Houston, Texas recorded between approximately 1900 and 1970. Five volumes are bound and one is unbound. The pages of the bound volumes are numbered consecutively within each volume. The sixth or unbound volume and is composed of loose sheets, and the pages are numbered but are not in order. The plat maps are not indexed. In addition, the collection contains a separate group of six subdivision plat maps that date from 1961 to 1981, and maps and engineering drawings for the Memorial Chase, Section 3 subdivision dated 1971 to 1973.
Detailed List of Contents
- Volume 1 (bound), Houston Map Company subdivision plat maps, 1-807 (Item 1)
- Volume 2 (bound), Houston Map Company subdivision plat maps, 808-1476 (unlabeled on front) (Item 2)
- Volume 3 (bound), Houston Map Company subdivision plat maps, 1479-2195 (Item 3)
- Volume 4 (bound), Houston Map Company subdivision plat maps, 2196-2946 (Item 4)
- Volume 5 (bound), Houston Map Company subdivision plat maps, 2959- (Item 5)
- Volume 6 (unbound), Houston Map Company subdivision plat maps, loose sheets, pages numbered but not in order (Item 6)
- Loose subdivision maps (not part of 6 volume set) (Ovs folder 1)
  - Maplewood South subdivision, Section 4, 1961 (Ovs folder 1, Item 1)
  - Windsor Village subdivision, Section 5, 1961 (Ovs folder 1, Item 2)
  - Northcliffe subdivision, Section 1, 1976 (Ovs folder 1, Item 3)
  - Parkway Forest subdivision, Section 5, 1976 (Ovs folder 1, Item 4)
  - Westwood subdivision, 1977 (Ovs folder 1, Item 5)
  - Sugar Mill subdivision, Section 5 replat, 1981 (Ovs folder 1, Item 6)
- Memorial Chase subdivision, Section 3 (1972 – 73), f/k/a Thameswood, Section 1 (1971), a subdivision of 72 acres out of the Ezekiel Ballard Survey, located at the corner of Old Louetta Road and Cossey Road, Harris County, Texas (Ovs folder 2)
  - Map of subdivision, December 1972 (Ovs folder 2, Item 1)
    rendered in ink on “mylar” or acetate film, recorded with Harris County Clerk, September 1973
  - Map of Cossey Road Drainage Ditch Right of Way, November 1971 (Ovs folder 2, Item 2)
    ink on vellum
  - Map of Details of Channel, July 1971 (Ovs folder 2, Item 3)
  - Land Survey and Field Notes (Ovs folder 2, Item 4)
- Engineering drawings for streets, water distribution, storm drainage, and sanitary sewer systems for Memorial Chase, Section 3, 1972-1973 (Ovs folder 3)
  ink on “mylar” or acetate film
- Subdivision maps (Ovs folder 4)
  diazo prints on paper
  - Memorial Chase subdivision Section 3, 1972 (Ovs folder 4, Item 1)
  - Memorial Chase subdivision Section 3, 1973 (Ovs folder 4, Item 2)
- Subdivision maps for Thameswood subdivision, Section 1, July 1971, June 1972 (Ovs item 1)
  2 sheets, ink on “mylar” or acetate film, (drafts, never submitted to county clerk)